Very good and welcome one more day to
beta tech for those of you who are new to
the channel here we talk about software and
technology and specifically in this series
we talk about design patterns we are going
to explain one by one each pattern looking at
their uses and explaining them with
examples if you still don't know what a
design pattern is I'll leave the beginning of the
series up here and in the
description and today we are going to talk about the
strategy pattern this pattern is a
behavioral pattern so it is a
pattern that serves to encapsulate logic
the objective of the pattern is to be able to have
different algorithms different logic
encapsulated in order to have the ability to
change from one to another in a
very elegant way but to understand it
elegantly let's look at a basic example
with a video game specifically we will
see it with Pokemon or a
somewhat incipient version of what a Pokemon game would be
in our version of the game we have
several types of attacks we have
special attacks physical attacks
attacks that can cause a certain change
of state in the enemy Pokemon or
even attacks that change the weather
changes in the state of the battle the
state of what would be
the game environment attacks
by  therefore they cause an effect they do something
do damage to the rival it could be one of
these effects for example another could
be to make the rival pokemon flee if we
start programming without thinking a little
before we will end up with a code
similar to this where we check each
type of attack each effect that can be
performed and we execute the
corresponding instructions the attack causes a
change of state we have the code for
it if the attack instead changes the
weather in 50% of the cases we
also have its code plugged in
but all this can get very ugly
quickly the last time I measured it in
pokemon there were more than 700
different attacks how can we program this
without going crazy without filling our
code with yves for each special case and
the use of the switch that we know is not worth it
a possible solution is the
strategic pattern as we have been
saying the strategy pattern allows to
execute different logics the key
is to create objects that represent
these strategies these strategies
obviously follow the same pattern, that is to
say they implement an interface or inherit
from an abstract class so they are
usable
in a polymorphic way which is what we are
trying to achieve in the case of
pokemon for example  we could define
an interface that defines the
execute attack function this function receives as a
parameter an object that obviously
has to be like the input of this
function which in our case is the
instance of the battle itself we can
assume that in this object where we have
the battle we have the pokemon that
are currently fighting the
weather configuration the type of
terrain let's go a set of variables
that define the current state of the combat
with this defined abstraction we already have
all the tools to apply the
pattern the important part of the pattern is
that the function that is going to execute the
attacks does not depend on any
specific attack it does not matter what attacks have been
selected it depends on the abstraction
therefore any class that inherits
or implements this extraction can be
used indifferently for
example if we want an attack that changes
the weather to rain we can implement
a strategy that does the same if we
want one that lowers the enemy's defense
for example we can
implement it in the same way in another
class
depending on the attack you select we
can use one strategy or another
and the best of all is that we can
invent any type of attack that does whatever it does we will
not have to
modify the function
that uses them for any reason with this flexibility we
gain many things and  once
the structure is set up there is nothing that
limits us in what we can do in the
attacks that we can program that we
want to program an attack that freezes
the opponent lowers their defense and suddenly
puts rain we can make a
strategy what we want to do another that
lowers the speed of the enemy and burns it we
can also do them as we are
getting attacks it is very
easy to program them and most
importantly it does not imply any change
in what would be the general code of the
combat so that saves you a lot of
headaches some of you will
also have realized that
this can be combined with another pattern and
that when we want to complicate
our attacks even more it starts to get a
little lame leave me a comment if
seeing this code you know what patterns
could be used in case we
wanted for example to have attacks
with multiple effects and to be able to combine
these effects
freely following the
strategic pattern you can play a lot with it
and to see a little more some other
uses outside of video games let's
put another example blogs most
applications output what some site
normally to the console but what happens
if suddenly we want our
program to not have the logs  to the console
but to a file or even
send them to a server through what
is h ttp or sockets seen in a certain way
the fact of creating blogs to print something
could be considered a strategy that would
happen like this instead of
directly calling the block function in the
console let's encompass this logic in a
strategic pattern
we could define an interface called
the blogger whose function is the
fact of writing a function of yours that you
know is called white or blogs and
we want everything to work as until
now we implement the function in a
class called console blogger that does
the blog council like the first console
this implementation does the same as before
but if now we want to change and
write to a file we can
simply implement another logger I
can call it file over
all over to file or whatever we want
this way we don't have to change the
behavior of the
program we have delegated all this logic
to the set of strategies of the
bloggers we have explained the
strategic pattern and now we can block what we
want where we want the
u ml diagram of this pattern is not very complex and we
can see it right now on the screen
on the one hand we have the context of the
context that would be the thing or the function
or the  class or whatever
our strategies use and the
base interface of the interface or the abstract class
of these strategies defines what would be
the signatures not the functions that
all these logics have to implement in order to be
used in a polynomial way
each individual strategy is a class
that implements these functionalities in
the pokemon example the context would be
the execution of the battle turn the
function that implements the logic of the
turn and each strategy would be the
implementation of the specific attack in the
blogger example the context would be
any class of our application
that wants to obviously output something
some type of file or to the console or
write something in general and each
strategy would be each logic of
writing something to the screen the fact of
calling the console what would be a
strategy for example the case of doing
an
http to send the logs some
online service could also be another and the
best thing is that they are independent as I
said before the context does not need to
know what specific implementation is being
used as I said the
strategy pattern is a great way to delegate
functionalities that can change
over time whenever we
have a certain logic that can
change it
is worth stopping for a moment to think
if we can use this pattern another
example that comes to mind  to the head so
quickly in fact in an example that I
recently found at work is a
case where we are developing a
software that solves
optimization problems to solve these
optimization problems there are several
rival methods algorithms can be
solved with algorithms like
local search like high flying or even with
families of genetic algorithms the idea
was that we could change algorithms
in a simple and easy way so we
could get metrics from each one and
compare the different solutions
basically we use the
strategy pattern and where each
individual strategy are the different
optimization algorithms and therefore we could
change between them without affecting
any other part of the code you can
also see it as if you were
developing
a family of plugins they are like parts
where you can place some things or
place others and they fit together like a puzzle
therefore you end up making your
program very modular so you can
combine the different parts to
achieve different functionalities
I hope you liked the video if you did do
not hesitate to subscribe and hit
the bell since there are
more patterns coming in this series and without much
more
thank you very much for watching me see you in the
next video bye